Last year I made a video on health
insurance policies in India in 2025.
>> [music]
>> The comment section of that video was
unlike anything I've seen before. People
were just extremely grateful for all the
rigor and hard work that went into it,
and so I thought that let me do it again
for 2026.
A lot has changed in 2026. One, the GST
has actually gone away.
>> [music]
>> So, in health insurance policies have
become a lot more affordable. Two, the
underlying insurer data has changed,
which means some of the companies that
were doing well last year are not doing
as well and vice versa. So, we'll get
into all of that. So, here's what
today's video is. I went through 31
companies, all the insurance companies.
[music]
We had a long list of 18 policies that I
identified from those,
>> [music]
>> and then we finally have a short list of
six policies
that are going to be valuable for you.
>> [music]
>> You will also learn what is the premium
amount for a 35-year-old couple with a
2-year-old son
with a cover of 1 crore rupees, right?
So, that's also something that I'll
share. I can also guarantee that you
will hear about one new policy that you
probably haven't heard of before,
which I found quite interesting, and you
will hear about two policies that
everybody keeps marketing, but actually
didn't fit the cut. With that, make sure
you stick around till the end because
this one's going to be worth your time.
Before I actually get into the companies
and the policies, I want to share how I
think about health insurance and what
mental model you could possibly borrow
from me. A lot of people ask that what
is a good coverage amount that I should
go with. Now, think of health insurance
policies objective. The only objective
of a health insurance policy is to
protect you and your family from
financial ruin.
The medical bill should not devastate
your family. That's the objective. The
objective is not to get petty cash back.
Hey, my annual expenses are 1 lakh
rupees. Can I get a policy for say
20,000 rupees that is going to give me
that 1 lakh rupee cash back and
therefore I get 5x returns? That is not
how you think of health insurance.
If because if that 1 lakh rupee is
insignificant to you and you can
basically borrow from friends and family
and pay them off, or it actually comes
out from your salary, then do not you
don't need a policy for that 1 lakh
rupee. Just pay it off because it's a
one-off, right? At least the way I think
of health insurance is that if there is
a large bill that can truly break my
back and likely to devastation of my
finances, that is what I need to
safeguard myself against, not these
petty cash expenses medical bills.
If you have that clarity, then it'll
become a lot easier for you to select
your policies, select what you want to
go for, and so on. So, I would highly
encourage you to change your mental
model
and think about the large expenses. Now,
how much cover should you get? That
answer varies for different people. For
some people it could be 10 lakh, 15 lakh
that could lead to financial ruin of
your family. For some people it's
larger. It could be 1 crore, 2 crore
rupees, right? And so therefore, how
much cover should you get? The answer
lies within you. You have to take a look
at your finances and understand what is
it that can lead to financial ruin in
your family and take a cover for that.
That number will probably sound really
big, which means it's the right number.
And there are ways to cut the premium by
taking an aggregate deductible or a
co-pay, things we'll discuss later on in
the video, but that's how you should
think about health insurance. With that,
now let's jump into the actual companies
that we've gone through. Before we
proceed, a quick shout-out to today's
sponsor, Ditto Insurance. They're a zero
spam company that gives you free,
honest, and unbiased advice regarding
your insurance policies across term and
health.
It's a platform that I personally use to
buy my insurance policies as well. Few
things I like about Ditto. One, they are
spam free. They will not you get to book
a call, you can chat with them on
WhatsApp, and they will not spam you.
You know how how annoying that gets.
Two,
Ditto is actually unbiased. They will
listen to your needs, your family's
needs, your existing policies, and then
go through the fine print with you of
all the different policies, and
therefore recommend what works well for
you. And third, and most important, in
the time of you actually wanting to get
a claim, they will help support you
there. If your claim gets stuck, they
will fight on your behalf,
and all of that for free. So, you can
use the link in the description and book
a call with Ditto senior advisor. Thank
you, Ditto, for sponsoring today's
video. I also want to call out that the
policies that I'm going to be talking
today are not influenced by Ditto. Those
are my filters and my recommendations
and my short lists.
That has nothing to do with Ditto's
influence on the video. Okay, let's jump
in. This is the meat of the video. We
are going to get into the Excel sheet
that I made. This is the list of 31
insurers that we have put together.
These are all the different 31 insurance
companies in the country that offer
health insurance. There is a There is a
stringent criteria put together against
these three metrics. Let's first
understand the metrics and then I'll
walk you through what the criteria is.
The first metric is CSR, which basically
means claim settlement ratio. This is an
average over the last 3 years from 2022
to 2025.
In my last year's video, this data was
from 2021 to 2024, so it's actually been
updated to this year. The definition is
claims settled upon the total number of
claims average over 3 years, right?
Pretty straightforward.
This basically shows that if you are
asking the company for a claim, how many
of those claims are actually getting
honored, right? That's as simple as
that. The higher the better.
For the purpose of this video, the
criteria that I've taken is CSR should
be greater than 90%, right? Cool. Next,
we have ICR. ICR stands for incurred
claim ratio.
It basically means amount of claims paid
upon the amount of premiums that were
collected in a financial year.
The way to understand this is that if
you are an insurance company, you get
100 rupees in terms of premiums from all
your customers, you get some claims,
what percentage of that 100 rupees are
you actually giving giving back to the
customers as claims? If this number is
too low, then that means the company is
being extremely conservative, denying a
lot of claims, or not paying out claims
in full. And so you don't want this
number to be very low. I'll give you an
example here. So, if you look at this,
say 58% Niva Bupa, 58% not good. Why are
they holding back so much money? Why are
they not actually giving that claim back
to the customers, right? So, that's one.
Let's look at the other extreme.
Oriental, 112%. How are they able to
give claims worth 112 rupees when they
didn't when they only got premiums worth
100 rupees, right? They are financially
stressed.
And you will see a lot of the other
different government companies actually
fall into the same criteria. New India
is at 103, Oriental is 112, United is
99. And for this reason, we are not
going to be looking at public sector
companies
in this particular video because they
are financially stressed. The reason
they are financially stressed is because
a lot of the government employees are
actually being insured under these
companies, and they have to honor those
claims.
And therefore, it is just unfortunate
that they are financially stressed. In
the short term, it could play out. Look,
if you have a policy and if you keep
getting your claims, great. But I'm
taking a long-term decision here, right?
I don't want to be stuck with a company
where there's a risk that I could be
caught on the wrong side because of
financial mismanagement. And so that's
why I personally stay away from health
insurance from these
public sector companies. On ICR, the
criteria is that the ICR should be
between 65 to 85%, which means the
company is financially managed well and
also not very conservative and stringent
in terms of giving out claims.
Third is complaints per 10,000 claims.
This is, as the name suggests, very very
simple. Number of complaints per 10,000
claims. My number here is it should be
less than 22. Why 22? Last year's
industry average was 22. This year's is
actually 27. I took 22 last year's, and
so I'm going to take the same 22 this
year. I think it's a pretty stringent
filter.
One call-out here. Health insurance
companies which only provide health
insurance have slightly higher
complaint rate, and so you can take that
into your consideration as you're going
into this. And general insurance
companies like say a Bajaj General is at
three because they also give out life
insurance, they give out auto insurance,
and the complaints are typically lesser.
But say for example, a Star. Now, Star
has a complaint rate of 52, which is
really high. Right? Now, you could say
that hey, they are only health insurance
company, but I don't buy that. I don't
want to go through such a harrowing
experience and buy a policy where the
complaint rate is so high, and therefore
you take your own call. But for my
particular
filtering, I have taken the complaint
rate as 22. The good news is all of this
data will be available with you. I will
leave a link to it in my description. Go
to my Substack. I will leave this Google
Sheet there. Just subscribe to the
Substack and you'll get this Google
Sheet. It's for free. So, you can use
it, share it with your friends and
family for whenever you need to decide
your own health insurance policy. On the
basis of that criteria, we have these
eight companies that I have
short-listed, and we are going to be now
evaluating their policies. The eight are
Bajaj General, ACKO, Go Digit, SBI
General, Tata AIG, Aditya Birla, ACKO,
and Liberty.
Why is Tata AIG here in yellow? Because
their claim settlement ratio is actually
89, which is lower than the criteria I
had set of 90%. Why have I still taken
it into account? Because last year their
claim settlement ratio was actually 96%.
So, I'm taking this as a blip on the
radar, but I want to call it out in case
this is a criteria you want to stay away
from, you can you can weed out Tata AIG.
But for my purpose, I'm going to
continue with it because they actually
have a pretty solid policy. Now, let's
go one level deeper. Out of these
different
eight companies, there are these 18
policies that I looked at.
There are three exceptions here. ICICI
Lombard Elevate Combo, Niva Bupa
ReAssure 3.0, and Care Supreme. I'll
come to that in the end. But the idea
here is to include these three even
though the companies are not very good,
is because I know a lot of you will get
these policies missold, and so I want to
make sure
I would say missold is a harsh word, but
because I know a lot of you have these
policies, or when you are actually
talking to different agents, you will
get these policies because they are
marketed really aggressively. And so I
want to make sure that I cover them and
you have full visibility into how I
think about these policies, right? Now,
let's understand these six filters one
by one. First one is 1 crore cover.
Straightforward. I want a policy that
has a big enough coverage, and so 1
crore cover is a big one. Second is no
room rent cap. This is an extremely
important filter. If you don't already
know, let me explain it with an example.
In simple terms, what this means is that
some of the policies say that if you get
admitted in a hospital, you can only get
admitted in a particular category of
room.
That room category says a single AC
room. Now, if you go to the hospital and
a single AC room is not admitted, but
you need to get your treatment done now
because it's urgent, and you get
admitted into a double AC room. So,
let's understand with numbers. Single AC
room cost is 10,000 rupees, which is
covered. Double AC room is 20,000
rupees,
and so you get admitted there thinking
that the difference is only 10,000
rupees. It's okay, I'll pay that out of
pocket. But that is where most people
make the mistake because what will end
up happening is when you actually submit
your invoice for the claim approval if
your entire bill is say
1 lakh rupees they will not just deduct
the 10,000 of the incremental charges of
double AC room but they will slash your
entire claim by 50%. Why 50%? Because
that's the difference between your
double AC room and your single AC room.
Your double AC your single AC room is
50% cheaper than your double AC room and
so your 1 lakh rupee
bill will actually get slashed to 50,000
when it comes to claim. And so be very
very careful of this room rent limit. I
want to make sure that you understand
this really well. Go through the policy
and understand this clause in great
detail because this can lead to a lot of
heartbreak later. Third filter is no
sub-limits, no disease sub-limits. This
basically means that some companies
actually put upper cap on a particular
disease. Say for example your policy
coverage amount is 4 lakh rupees. And
you have a disease sub-limit on cardiac
arrest for 2 lakh rupees. You go into
the hospital, you get your procedure
done for 3 lakh rupees. You will not get
the entire 3 lakh rupees even though
your entire policy is for 4 lakh rupees
you will only get 2 lakh rupees you will
have to pay 1 lakh out of your pocket.
So that is what disease sub-limit means.
You do not want your policy to have any
disease sub-limit. So I've taken that as
a third filter. Fourth is consumables.
Consumables is very simple. Think of it
as syringes, IVs, masks, PPF kits and so
on and so forth. Sounds small but
typically a bill in the hospital has 30
to 40% in consumables. And so when
you're actually submitting your claim
they will deduct all the consumables and
then you will be short changed. So you
want consumables to be covered. In a lot
of the policies these are not covered.
There are four different annexures in
this. So again a lot of detail there you
should check it out later. But a lot of
policies give you a rider for
consumables. This is one of the most
important riders as you're thinking of
buying a policy. Just make sure you're
thinking of the consumable rider as
well. Fourth is co-pay. Co-pay means
sharing the bill. You it basically means
that if you are if your bill is worth
100 rupees and you have a 10% co-pay
that means you have to pay 10 rupees and
the insurance company will pay 90
rupees. Ideally you do not want co-pay.
You want the insurance company to pay
the entire bill. But in some cases if
you can't afford a big premium
some policies actually give you this
add-on benefit that add a co-pay.
And that will bring your premium down
considerably. So it's not a bad option
for those who can't afford a heavy
premium. But if you can then stay away
from co-pay. Have a 100% co-pay policy
which means that the insurance company
pays the entire amount of co-pay.
Right? So I think those are the key
filters and waiting period and all is is
good to have if you have any
pre-existing diseases. There's a lot of
detail on this. I will not cover this to
make this video crisp but
I've also mentioned all the waiting
periods here for you to take a call
later. So when you run all these 18
policies through these six filters a lot
of them just get dropped off very very
easily because they are failing on one
of these filters, right? The ones that
come out on top is HDFC Ergo Optima
Secure 2X. 2X is basically that you get
2X the amount of coverage from day one.
We'll get into this in the next section.
Next is Tata AIG Medicare Premier. Third
is the Aditya Birla Active One NXT,
Aditya Birla Active One Max, Acko
Platinum Health and SBI Health Alpha
Ultimate. Right? There are also others
like HDFC Ergo Super Secure 3X which was
eliminated because it has a 3-year
lock-in mandatory. You have to buy it
for 3 years and then the premium becomes
like 1 lakh 5,000 which is pretty high.
So that's why I didn't select it but you
could check it out if that premium is
okay for you.
Third is Tata AIG like this is another
one that got eliminated which is Tata
AIG Medicare Select because it has a
room rent cap. Tata
AIG Medicare Plus I will cover this
briefly in my next section. It's a good
budget alternative to the Tata AIG
Medicare Premier.
And then all of these other policies are
not I'm not going to spend too much time
on because they got eliminated for
something or the other except Acko
Platinum and Acko Platinum Light. I will
cover this in my next section as a
alternative to Acko Platinum.
This is a budget alternative and not
eliminated. Let me fix that for you.
Yeah. So that's that's where we're at.
Three policies I want to briefly cover
here is ICICI Lombard Elevate Combo. Now
the problem with this is it has a room
rent cap and that's why I don't
particularly like it. It's a highly
searched policy. Um
but like the single AC room rent cap is
something that I don't particularly
like. Consumables also comes with a
rider. So which is okay if you can get
the rider it's fine.
And most importantly the company metrics
for ICICI Lombard are pretty weak. Their
CSR is 85% which is below the 90%
threshold that we had put for ourselves,
right? Let's see what the complaint rate
is.
The complaint rate is 11. So okay so
complaint rate is not bad. But the claim
settlement ratio is pretty bad.
Next is Niva Bupa ReAssure 3.0. Here the
problem is that this has disease
sub-limits. Actually the problem here is
that robotic surgery is not covered in
this is what I learned. Which you should
double check all of the things that I'm
saying here by the way. This is based on
my research. I might be wrong.
But from what I could tell robotic
surgery is not covered and robotic
surgery is now a very common part of a
lot of the different procedures. Be it a
knee procedure or a heart procedure or
anything robotics are being used
somewhere or the other. And so if that's
not covered then that would lead to a
lot of heartache later in terms of claim
settlement.
The other is significant gap in terms of
ICR is 58% and complaints are 43. Both
really really bad. And so that's the
reason why I would not personally buy
Niva Bupa ReAssure 3.0.
The last one is Care Supreme. Again here
there is a room rent cap which I don't
particularly like. And again micro level
company metrics for Care is pretty bad.
42 is the complaints. Not good. ICR is
59% again lower than the 65% criteria
that we had set out for ourselves. So
not good. But you tell me in the
comments if you have any of these
policies what is your experience been
with them. I think we only get richer as
a community if we can share our
experiences with each other. I don't
have these policies so I can't vouch for
them. I'm just going by the data that I
see. I would really appreciate if you
can leave comments if you own any of
these policies and share your experience
on how it has been. Thank you so much to
all of you. I actually want to go do
that. Let's move on to the next section.
18 policies went in six policies came
out. Let's go through them one by one. I
will try and keep this section quick.
But all the premium indicative in this
here you will be seeing is for a family
floater plan. So 35-year-old couple
husband wife with a 2-year-old son in a
metro city, right? That's how we're
going to be approaching this. The six
policies here are HDFC Ergo Optima
Secure, Tata AIG Medicare Premier,
Aditya Birla Active One NXT, Aditya
Birla Max, Acko Platinum Health and SBI
Health Alpha Ultimate.
Let's go one by one through our filters.
Let's start with HDFC Ergo Optima Secure
2X. For transparency this is the policy
that I have. I've also mentioned that in
the past.
Why do I like it? Look 1 crore covers
available.
Cashless hospitals 163 in Gurgaon which
is pretty healthy compared to the rest
of them. Room rent cap is not there.
Disease sub-limit is not there.
Consumables are included as a part of
the policy. No added riders needed.
Pretty simple.
I also want to quickly talk about this
2X. What this 2X means is that if you
have taken a sum insured of 50 lakh
rupees with this 2X that 50 lakh becomes
1 crore starting day one. So it's a good
way to get a high coverage at a lower
premium. That's what this 2X means.
Now the waiting period here is 3 years
standard across the industry.
Restoration benefit yes. What does
restoration benefit mean? Now think of
restoration benefit as like a mobile
data top-up. Say for example your
balance ran out in the same year. For
your subsequent bill your policy will be
recharged then you can continue to make
multiple claims against it.
This is especially important for family
floater plans because say for example
multiple people fall ill unfortunately
in the same year. You have one claim
against one person.
And say later on in the year you have a
second claim against another person. You
want to be make sure and sure that that
claim goes through and that's why if it
if the restoration benefit is there then
you can actually get the claim on that
as well. And so that's why restoration
benefit is important. I don't want to go
too much into detail into this. You can
read up on this on your own time.
But it is important for a family floater
plan so keep that in mind as you're
thinking about this.
Next is aggregate deductible option. Yes
it is available.
What is aggregate deductible option? I
will cover that separately later.
And finally co-pay. There is no co-pay
in this which is again a good deal. None
There is no co-pay in any of these
policies so that's a good thing. What
are the special benefits? I've already
covered this. The 2X base cover from day
one and unlimited restore rider
available. So this restoration benefit
if you want unlimited restore that as
many number of times in the year you
want that rider is available separately
if you want. 2X base cover is actually
pretty cool because
actually let's get into the premium then
you'll see how. So 1 crore cover for
this policy costs 34,427.
But you don't need to take a 1 crore
cover if you truly want a 1 crore
coverage because you can take a 50 lakh
rupee cover for HDFC Optima Secure.
Because it's 2X it becomes 1 crore. So
you actually get it at a lower premium
30,582.
On top of this if you add an aggregate
deductible of 1 lakh rupees then this
30,582 becomes 14,264.
By the way this is really low given last
year's numbers which are much higher.
And that's because the GST is not there.
So that has actually had a huge impact
on the premiums. They've gone down a lot
more.
But let me now briefly talk about what
aggregate deductible is. Aggregate
deductible means say for example you
have a bill of
5 lakh rupees. The company will not give
you
the amount for the first 1 lakh. They
will not respect that claim. They will
only give you the remaining 4 lakhs. How
does this help? Well if you have a
corporate insurance policy that is worth
3 lakh 5 lakhs. Most people have that.
Then you can use that as the aggregate
deductible component to come in.
And then you can use your personal
insurance policy for the larger bills.
Remember the principle we set out at the
start of the video that you don't want
to be optimizing for your petty medical
insurance expense. At least that's how I
think about it. You might disagree. You
want to be optimizing for the large
expenses. And so this is a good way to
get a large cover
at a affordable premium by using your
corporate policy to cover for this
aggregate deductible. And as As result
of which your premium really goes down.
Yeah? So, I also have an aggregate
deductible on my policy. I know some of
you might not agree with it, but this is
my video and so I'm just sharing what I
follow.
Uh okay, moving on.
Merit, it's a great value pick. You will
see it's it's a pretty good one. You
could consider this policy. There is one
more here which is HDFC Super Secure.
Now, Super Secure, the difference
between Optima Secure and Super Secure
is that Super Secure is 3x. So, if you
buy a 50 lakh rupee policy, that will
become 1.5 crore from day one. It's a 3x
as opposed to Optima Secure's 2x. The
only caveat here is that you have to buy
for a minimum of 3 years in one go and
that essentially jacks up your premium a
fair bit. But, in case you are okay with
paying for 3 years, you can also
consider Super Secure. Right? That
covers the first policy, HDFC Ergo
Optima Secure. Moving on to the next
one, the Tata AIG Medicare Premier. 1
crore cover, yes. Cashless hospitals,
116, not too bad. All of this is good.
Room rent cap is not there. Disease sub
limit is not there. Consumables are
included. Waiting period is 2 years.
This is a good one. So, if you have any
pre-existing diseases, then the waiting
year waiting period here is 2 years,
which is amazing
in in case that matters to you.
Restoration benefit is there. Aggregate
deductible option is there, but only
50,000, not 1 lakh, 5 lakhs, whatever.
Um yeah, so only 50,000. Another tip I
want to call out here is that actually
different portals and different websites
have a different aggregate deductible
option. So,
you could actually call up Tata AIG and
ask them and they might be able to do it
on the call center and give you a
different deductible option which might
not be available on their website. So,
always call them once while you're
buying this because they might be able
to offer you something on the phone
which is better than what you're getting
on their online portal or on another
aggregator portal.
Co-pay is not there.
Um the special benefits that a lot of
special benefits in this. One
international cover is included. OPD,
dental, maternity, they're all included
after 2 years, which is these are all
great benefits. But, then it comes at a
cost. The 1 crore cover of this this is
by far the most expensive policy out
there.
Uh 57,179 is the 1 crore cover for a
35-year-old couple living in Gurgaon
with a 2-year-old son. Um the 50 lakh
cover is 43,393. If I were to take a 50
lakh cover with a 50,000 deductible,
then that comes to 40,248. Again, pretty
expensive, right?
Most comprehensive policy, but most
expensive policy. So, you take your own
call. There is a more affordable version
budget version of this which is called a
Medicare Plus this policy. Um this is
cheaper, but the difference here is that
there is no restoration benefit. So,
take your own call. In case that's not
something that you want, you can go with
this. The deductible here is maximum of
3 lakh or 5 lakh only. Um and suitable
if, you know, budget [snorts] is your
priority. So, that's on Tata AIG
Medicare Premier.
Next is the stable of Aditya Birla
Aditya Birla One Next and Aditya Birla
One Max. Personally, I think Aditya
Birla One Next is an interesting policy.
Again, similar to HDFC Optima Secure 2x,
this is also 2x. So, this is 50 lakh
plus
another 50 lakh extra. Similar to what
the HDFC Optima Secure does. Cashless
hospitals, very good coverage. Aditya
Birla actually has one of the best
coverage of cashless hospitals across
the country. Um room rent cap, none.
Disease sub limits, none. Consumables,
you have to buy an extra rider. So, make
sure that you're buying this. If you buy
the Aditya Birla One Max, then that is
the rider is not needed to be bought.
It's actually included, so it simplifies
it. Um waiting period is the same, 3
years 3 years. Restoration benefit is
there in this, both great, yes yes.
Aggregate deductible option is available
on the Aditya Birla website only. So,
like I was saying, the websites, call
centers, aggregators, all have different
plans available at them. So, just check
with them, but ABG's website you'll get
an aggregate deductible. Co-pay is not
there in any of these, so amazing. Um
I think I will skip through this
quickly.
The 50 lakh cover here is
something that I looked at. Aditya Birla
One NXT, the cost for this policy is
that 36,849
rupees for a 1 crore cover. This is with
the consumables rider. I've included
that. And this basically becomes 2 crore
coverage from day one, right? So, that's
amazing. If you want to go with a 50
lakh rupee cover, it's 29,803. Again,
pretty compelling. This now becomes a 1
crore policy essentially for 29,803.
There is no aggregate deductible that I
could find. Maybe you could find it on a
different portal. But, in case you find
that, then this will become even lower.
But, this actually becomes pretty cheap
now if you think about it because
without a deductible, you're getting a 1
crore policy for 29,803,
which is actually the cheapest across
the board. So, you could you could check
that out.
Um yeah, I think that's pretty much it
on NXT. Aditya Birla One Max is
basically a simpler alternative to NXT.
The consumable rider is already built
into this.
Um and yeah, there is no rider that is
needed here. The only drawback here is
that it is not a 2x policy and so you
will have to buy a 1 crore policy here
and that becomes expensive at 36,375
compared to say this 29,803
rupees.
Um so yeah, that's on the Aditya Birla
stable. All right, next is Acko Platinum
Health. This is another interesting
policy. Acko is doing some pretty good
work in the health insurance space. 1
crore cover is yes. Room rent is not
there. Disease sub limits is not there.
Consumables are included. Waiting period
zero, but it comes with a caveat. You
What is the caveat here? This is a
screenshot from the Acko website that
you need a detailed health evaluation to
be eligible for this plan. So, they will
send somebody to do your medical checkup
detailed before they actually offer you
this plan. So, keep that in mind. This
zero years is not actually zero years
because if you don't have a pre-existing
disease, then only is it a zero years,
right? So, that's that. Acko has removed
restoration benefit from last year to
this year. Last year they had
restoration benefit. This year they
don't have restoration benefit. So, just
keep that in mind if this is something
that you care about. I don't know why
they removed it, but they have.
Aggregate deductible option also I could
not find. Maybe if you call them, you
might be able to find it. Co-pay is not
there. Everything else is pretty much
the same, but it's pretty cheap. 24,520
is actually the cheapest uh health
insurance policy that you can buy for 1
crore cover.
Um and that's essentially the value
proposition. They give very very good
value. Um the other version of this is
Acko Platinum Light. If you do not get
Acko Platinum Health because of
any pre-existing diseases,
um then they will offer you the Acko
Platinum Light where the waiting period
is 3 years and there is an option of a
deductible. So, you can check out. The
premium will go even lower uh because
when you add a deductible, it will it
will become even lower. So, this is
another option you can check out.
Last, but not the least, this was
actually something that I found um while
uh talking to SBI's call center because
this is not available on any aggregator
platform. And I quite like this policy.
I think it's an interesting policy that
not a lot of people are talking about.
SBI Health Alpha Ultimate, it's a new
product from SBI. Um 1 crore cover is
available. You only can buy this from
the SBI call center. At the website, you
only get it up to 25 lakh rupees. But,
if you call them on the call center,
then they will offer you the 1 crore
cover.
Um room rent cap is there via rider
though. You have to buy a separate
rider. This is what it looks like. Um
and this is a screenshot from their
actual website. Just
goes on to show how much I have
This is one video that takes the most
amount of time for me to make given I
have to go through all of these
different portals. But, anyway, um so
this is how it looks, reduction room
rent limit. If you're buying this, just
click on actual so that there is no room
rent limit and your premium goes
slightly up. Um so yeah, it's there is
no room rent limit. Just buy that extra
rider. Disease sub limit, not there. And
consumables, again, you have to buy a
rider to include that. Waiting period 3
years. Restoration benefit is there.
Aggregate deductible option is available
through the SBI call center. Co-pay is
not there.
Now, special benefits. They have gym
injuries, adventure sports, all of these
available as separate uh riders. Gym is
actually included as a part of the plan.
LASIK, if you want to get that done,
that is included. OPD is included.
Maternity is again included via rider.
Albeit the rider for maternity is
extremely expensive. I personally don't
recommend buying a maternity cover
because the
premium to benefit ratio is actually
pretty low. Um and so you're better off
just paying that maternity cost on your
own as opposed to buying paying a
company and then being restricted by all
of the different rules that comes along
with it. It's not worth it in my
opinion. The 1 crore cover for the SBI
Health Alpha Ultimate costs 33,304. The
50 lakh cover costs 29,336.
Um the aggregate deductible of 1 crore
policy with a 1 lakh deductible comes to
30,012, which is not bad.
I think it's a it's a good all-round
policy.
Um the only caveat is you'll have to buy
it directly from SBI. It's not available
on any aggregator, at least not that I
could find it. But, you tell me in the
comments if you can find it. That brings
us to the end of today's video. Before I
let you go, four things that you should
keep in mind. One, health insurance is
age-linked. The best time to buy a
health insurance policy was 5 years ago,
but the second best time is now because
the sooner you buy, the better the
premiums that you'll get. Point number
two, get a cover that is large enough.
Do this visualization exercise. Think of
a big amount of money that is going out
of your bank account for a health
emergency. That amount should squirm
make you squirm, make you uncomfortable.
That is the right amount of health
insurance coverage that you need to get.
Third point is that if that right amount
feels prohibited from a premium
standpoint, use your corporate policies
well. Use that as an aggregate
deductible to reduce the premium amount
and be smart about that. And fourth and
finally, do not believe every YouTube
video that you see out there, including
this one. I do not know your specific
situation, your specific circumstances.
Talk to an expert who can actually guide
you in that. Uh this is just some
research I have done, but there is a lot
more research that is exists around this
stuff. The folks at Ditto are something
I personally use. Spam free, free, uh
and unbiased. So, use the link in the
description to set up a call with the
senior advisors. And thank you. Share
this with as many people as you can. See
you all in the next one. Bye-bye.